<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boke of demaundes of the scyence of phylosophye, and astronomye, betwene kynge Boctus, and the phylosopher Sydracke.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3188A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840337</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16268)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 875:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boke of demaundes of the scyence of phylosophye, and astronomye, betwene kynge Boctus, and the phylosopher Sydracke.</title>
                  <author>Boccus, King.</author>
                  <author>Sidrac, 13th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge in the Duke of Suffolkes rentes, besyde charynge Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1550]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A different text from STC 3188.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and address from colophon; publication date estimated by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Questions and answers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ The Boke of Demaundes of the ſcyence of Phylo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſophye, and Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, Betwene kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Boctus, and the Phyloſopher Sydracke.</p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Sydracke.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Kynge Boctus.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, howe was the worlde made, and howe holdeth it. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>GOD made Heauen and water, &amp; when he wolde make man, after that the euyll Aungelles fell downe from heuen in abyſme. He ſayd that the world be made, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none forthwith was his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment done. And the worlde was fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med vpon the water as his pleaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was. And all the water that is in th<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ayre it abydeth vpon the erthe, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can not be ſo depe nor ſo parfound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but it muſt nedes abyde on the ert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and as ye ſhall vnderſtande that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame erth, and alſo this that is dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>couered hath other water vnder hym alſo, that ſuſtayneth it. For the foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of the erthe is the water, and the foundement of the water is the fyrmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and the one and the other
<pb facs="tcp:4834:5"/>hangeth and holdeth togyther by the fyrmamente, and by the myghte and wyll of God. GOD of his great myght made the worlde to the ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaunce of an egge, as in lykenes the ſhell of the Egge is the fyrmament, that enuyrons and goeth all aboute the world, and the whyte of the egge is the water that is betwene the fyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mament that enuyrons and goeth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute the erth. The yelke of the egge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the erth that enuyroneth all abou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with water, and ſet vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er. In lykewyſe as the yelke of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gge that is ſet and enuyroned all a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oute w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whyte of the egge. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eede that is betwene the yelke and he whyte of the egge, that be the fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes that be on earth, euen as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de is on the yelke &amp;, thus is the forme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. But then it is as rounde as a Bowle, that hath neyther heade nor tayle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:5"/>
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, mounteth the ſonne more vpwarde then he deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or deſcendeth he more then he mounteth. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>THe ſonne by the morowe when he ryſeth red and clere he moun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth alway tyll halfe the day be paſt, that is called mydday. And then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the halfe day, he deſcendeth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth lower, tyll he go downe, and as red ye may ſe the ſonne at his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge downe, as at his ryſynge, and as moche he deſcendeth downwarde as he mounteth vpwarde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, the ſonne doth he mounte &amp; deſcende as wel by nyght as by day. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>WHen the Sonne appereth to vs, heare, that he goeth downe and fayleth vs, he ſheweth to other folke
<pb facs="tcp:4834:6"/>in another countree, that be in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parte of the worlde, and he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth hym in his turnynge to them, that the day aprocheth to as he doth vs, when the daye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth and lygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs. And at after mydnyght, tyll it be day he goeth lower to them, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs waxeth hygher, for to them he aprocheth in the nyght, and to vs in the day, &amp; when he fayleth vs he ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereth vnto them i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another countre.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, why groweth the Moone, and at ſomtyme waxeth leſſe and leſſe. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>THe Moone appeareth &amp; ſemeth to vs that ſhe groweth, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whyle waxeth leſſe, and all this appereth to vs, for the ſonne and the tornyng of the fyrmament, for al the whyle that ſhe is agaynſt the ſonne, ſhe is couered, and appereth vnto vs
<pb facs="tcp:4834:6"/>that ſhe waxeth leſſe. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereth to vs that ſhe is al fayled and ſheweth nothyng, than ſhe is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched nyghe to the Sonne, and leſeth all her lyght, for the coueryng of the ſonne. And at the ſame poyncte that ſhe fautes all her lyght to vs, at the ſame poyncte the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e paſſeth her, for the mouement of the tyrmamente, &amp; then ſhe dyſcouereth on the other par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of the ſonne, and then ſhe is newe ſemynge to vs here, and for the feble ſyght that we haue, we maye not ſe her at that poyncte. And euerye .xv. dayes ſhe groweth, &amp; other .xv. day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſhe waneth and waxeth leſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon that in ſome place in the worlde, the Clyps of the Sonne and of the Moone maye be ſene, and in ſome place it maye not be ſene. Sydracke Anſwereth.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:7"/>
            <p>THe Sonne maketh his Clyps, aſwell by day as by nyght, and by nyght as by daye, for when we haue day here, other folkes haue in other places nyght, and when it is nyght here with vs, it is day w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them for the fyrmament neuer ceaſeth tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge, and therin a bydeth the ſonne the Moone, and the ſtarres, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyron and go aboute all the worlde, and at no tyme they fayle not theyr lyght, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr lyght fayleth to vs here, they ſhewe it to other folkes in other places, and when it fayleth other folkes there, it ſheweth to vs here. And al this is for the roundnes of the world, for the world is all rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de as an balle, for when the Sonne draweth lowe, he gyueth his lyghte to that parte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he draweth lowe to, and then it is derke behynde hym, as and a man helde a candell lyght befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re hym the vyſage of hym ſhuld haue
<pb facs="tcp:4834:7"/>the ſhadow. And ſo in lykewyſe doth the ſonne aboute the fyrmament, by cauſe of the roundnes of the worlde. This is the daye and the nyght, for God made the nyghte for the reſte of man, and for other creatures. And therfore when the Sonne is in the clyps here with vs, we haue it by day and therfore we may ſe it, and then it is nyght with other folkes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they maye not ſe it, for the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of the erth Alſo when the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is in the clyps w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other folkes they haue daye, and we haue nyght, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may ſe it, and we may not ſe it, for the ſhadowe of the earth. And lykewyſe is the Moone as the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in the clyps, when tyme and ſeaſon is, aſwell by daye as by nyght. And therfore it is day with vs when it is nyght with other folkes. Howe be it that the fyrmament maketh alway his turne for our day and our nyght
<pb facs="tcp:4834:8"/>is all one, for where ſoeuer they tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne they haue alway lyght &amp; reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and brightnes that God of his grace hath gyuen them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, is there any poyncte in the daye that is good. Sydracke Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>AT that poynct that the Moone maketh her turne at, the .xxxvi. poynctes after, thou ſhalte haue a good poyncte: &amp; from the poyncte at .C. lvij. poynctes, another. And from that at .CCC. lxxvij. poynctes, thou ſhalte haue another. And from that poyncte at .v. M. ij. poynctes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt haue another. And from the poyncte at .vij. C. xi. poynctes thou ſhalt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue another. And from the poynct at .CCC. xvi. poynctes thou ſhalte haue another. That is to ſay, poynctes in euery Moone where the .xxiiij. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the day and of the nyght ben.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:8"/>
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, howe ſhulde a man knowe the euyll poyncte. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>AT euery tyme that the moone is newe, thou ſhalt tell by .xvij. ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes .xvij. poynctes, and at euery ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the .xvij. poynctes, or as many houres as the Moone is newe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that day that poynctes after, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the thyrd, the fourth, &amp; the fyft be euyll, &amp; then ye ſhall counte yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many poynctes as ye haue tolde and counted before .v. poynctes after ben euyll poynctes. And alway to counte this counte, the houres begyn, whar the Sonne goeth downe, and the nyght and the daye be .xxiiij. houres. And they begyn at the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne goyng downe bycauſe the nyght was before the daye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:9"/>
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, is there any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther folkes vnderneth vs that ſe the lyght of the Fyrmamente as we do. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>FOr bycauſe of the roundnes of the worlde there are folkes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneth vs that ſeeth the lyght of the fyrmament as we do, and alſo theyr fete go agaynſt our fete, and that is for the hyghenes and longnes of the parties of the world and for his roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denes, for the Eeſt parte is moch hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er where the Sonne ryſeth, then the weſt parte where the Sonne goeth downe. When the ſonne ryſeth in the Eeſt, then it is dawnynge of the day in the weſt. And alſo when the ſonne goeth lowe in the weſt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is euyn nyght in the Eeſt, for the greatnes &amp; roundnes of the world, for whyle the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſhall make one ſhadowe on erth of .iiij. then ſhall the fyrmament ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<pb facs="tcp:4834:9"/>courſe in his towre .M. legues. It is not to be vnderſtand that the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſheweth not nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not ſo lowe as the erth, nor nye to it, but a great tyme and a great way from the erth aſmoche as the length of the erth is from the one heade to the other, and aſmoch agayne, and is more ferther for to go vp, then for to go downe.</p>
            <p>There is a lande an folkes dwellyng therin, that the Sonne abydeth not there but one houre of the day, and a none it is nyghte. There is another lande where it is darke alway as it were nyght. And whan it is in one place of world wynter, in another pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce it is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer. And whan it is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer there, it is in the other partes wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and all this is by the reaſon of the Sonne that taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, by the volent and wyll of God eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeare.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:10"/>
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, how longe, how large, and howe thycke is the world. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>FOrſoth the worlde is as moch of length, as of largeneſſe, and of thyckenes the ſame, for it is all as rounde as an apple. And who wolde go, from one heed to the other ryght through the worlde, and went euerye day well and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly, from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row tyll euen, and the brede of the ſee that is betwene Eeſt and weſt, were all ferme lande and erth, and all the world were as playne as the paume of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hande, no man might go from the one heed to thother, in leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen a .M. dayes, and the largeneſſe, and thyckenes is as moche.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, maye any man go aboute the worlde. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:10"/>
            <p>THere is no man that may go or turne aboute the worlde, and a man myght lyue a .M. yere and more, and all the earth were ferme &amp; playne, and yf he wolde go he ſhulde fynde ſo many countres, hylles, mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynes, and dales. That he myghte not paſſe them in no wyſe, and alſo he ſhuld fynde ſo moch drought and drye places, that he ſhulde not fynde one ſope of water. And alſo he ſhulde fynde many peryllous and dyuers beaſtes, and foules, that he ſhulde be ſlayne and deuoured, and yf he might paſſe all theſe perylles, yet he ſhulde fynde ſo great deſerte, where there is great obſcure and darkenes that he ſhulde ſe no ſyghte. And yf he ſhulde paſſe all this, yet he ſhulde fynde ſo great &amp; meruaylous chynes &amp; caues in the erth, by the which the ſee that is called the ſee Betee, that paſſeth thoroughe the lande, and partes one
<pb facs="tcp:4834:11"/>countre from another, and by many reaſons he might not go it. And yf it were ſo that a fowle ſhuld flye, yet he myght not do it, for the great thurſt and hunger that he ſhuld haue, for he ſhulde fynde no fode, and alſo for the great wyldernes, &amp; for other fowles that wolde ſlee and deuour hym, and for many other reaſons.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, how many lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des is there. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>THere is but one lande, but for the reaſon of the See that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth throwout it, and partꝭ it in .iii. partyes, therof there are named .iii. Countres, withouten Iles in the ſee, but all is one lande ferme, and all be vpon one foundement, and all GOD formed and made in one houre, and all at ones. And a man were all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnder the worlde, whiche were
<pb facs="tcp:4834:11"/>vnpoſſyble for any man to be there, but by the wyll of God he myght wel be, and went all aboute and behelde well, he ſhulde fynde that all the erth and lande were one as well there as the ſee is not, as there as ſhe is, for ſo perfounde and depe maye no man be vnder her, but that ſame earthe, hath yet other water vnder her, that ſuſtayneth her.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, myghte a man ſayle ſo longe in a ſhyp, and he had wynde and wether at his wyll, or the ſee, that he myght come nyghe to the place where the fyrmament tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth aboute. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>AND a man were in a ſhyp, and the ſee bare hym, and the wynde put hym forth alway forwarde, and ſayled .x. yere on the ſee or more, and that Shyp parted from the Eaſt, ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4834:12"/>ſhuld be a great whyle after that, or ſhe came into the weſt, and alſo and ſhe departed from the weſt ſhe ſhuld be as longe or ſhe aryued in the Eaſt And alſo in lykewyſe in the trauerſe and ouerthwart the world, and yf it ſo were that it ware the wyl of God that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were as great and as bol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and hardy as all the worlde, and he were nyghe vnto the fyrmament, where he turneth about by. M M le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues or more, the feere that he ſhuld haue when the fyrmament maketh his turne, and of the tempeſt &amp; noyſe that he maketh and of his mouynge that great and bolde hardy man, as all the world ſhuld be deed anone at that ſame houre, and ſhuld not lyue one houre, nor myght not, howe be it that a man were as hardye and as great as is aforeſayd, and yet the fir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mament ſeaſeth not alway to turne by the wyll of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:12"/>
            <head>¶ The kynge aſked, ſhall all the erth be enhabyted with folkes. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>AL the earth ſhall be enhabyted, and ſhalbe deuyded in .iij. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The fyrſt partye is named Aſye Le Grande, and is as great as the other two. And this partye dureth from Septentrion by Orient tyl myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye. The ſeconde partye is named Ewrope and dureth from Occydent vnto neptentrion. The thirde parti is named Auffryke that dureth from myddy vnto Occydent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kynge aſked in what place is paradyſe Terreſtre. Sydracke Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>PAradyſe terreſtre is in the fyrſt region of Aſye le grande towar Orient, and there is none erthly man
<pb facs="tcp:4834:13"/>that may come there but god or his Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels lede hym and guyde hym thy ther For this Paradyſe ſythen that Adam was eaſt and dryuen out ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of by an Aungell, anone forthwith it was enuironed al aboute with great fyre that dureth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the erth vnto the ſkie aboue that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may enter nor come therto. And alſo there is all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute Paradyſe great wylderneſſes where there is great multytude of many dyuers and peryllous beaſtes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kynge aſked, in what place is hell. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>HEll is in the myddes of Auffry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnder the erth and is ſet in the myddes of earth, as a karnell of an apple is in the myddes of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for as moche erth is there aboue as beneth. And there be the ſoules, that be dampned in great payne and turment without ende.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:13"/>
            <head>¶ The kynge aſked, may there come any tokens or Sygnes, that a man may ſe boldely out of heauen or hell. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Man may ſe ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly the waters that commeth from Paradyſe Terreſtre, for there is a well ſprynge of the which .iij. Ryuers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of it. And one of thoſe .iij. Ryuers go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth by the parties of myddy toward Orient, and falleth into the ſee of Oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cydent, and that aryſeth oute of hell agayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in the parties of Ynde. And the other two Ryuers, aryſeth agayne in Ewrope of an hyll there, &amp; there paſſe by many cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres, tyll they mete, and then they fall into the ſee, as nature requyreth. And alſo a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſe in Auffryke openly .ij. hylles, that be ſoupyrall of hell, &amp; they ceaſe not nether day nor night and be euer brennynge with fyerſe fyre.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:14"/>
            <head>¶ The Kynge aſked, what is the can ſe that the blode of a man, the bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the mary, and the waters gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth and waxeth leſſe and more. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>WHan God made the fyrmament the .vij. Planettes, and the .xij. Sygnes, and ſtablyſhed and orday<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned them for to lyght the world, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſtablyſſhed &amp; ordayned, as a lorde that the blode, and the braynes, and the mary of mankynde, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters alſo ſhuld waxe and wane as the Moone doth, that is more nere the erth then any of the other planettes And alſo ſhe groweth and waneth in heauen, but to vs here on erth it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth &amp; appereth to vs that ſhe grow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth &amp; waneth here. And all this is by cauſe of the mouement of the fyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; for the turne that ſhe maketh, for ſhe goeth all aboute the worlde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:14"/>
            <head>¶ The kynge aſked, is any man the worſe yf he be pore, or ſonne to a pore man, or bonde to another, or not ſo well fauoured as another. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>AS ſpiritually and againſt god a man is neuer the better, nor neuer the worſe for his riches, nor for his pouerte, nor for his euyll fauour, but for his workes and dedes if thou be ryche and puyſſaunt, and I poore, yet with all my pouerte, God hathe gyuen me forme of man, as he hath done to the, for as well am I borne of a woman and gotten of a man as thou arte. And alſo I haue a ſpryte as thou haſte. And I haue alſo my poore body all hole, and complet and my argumentes as thou haſt in thy ryche body. And when thou ſhalte de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte &amp; go to another worlde, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt go as poorely as I. And for thy ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:4834:15"/>nothynge may not be the better but onely by thy good dedes and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. And thoughe I be bonde, or ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to a bonde man, I am neuer the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſo that I lyue Godly and truly and clenly after the cours and nature of man. Such is the world, for ſome be riche and ſome be poore, and ſome be fayre and ſome fowle. And at theyr ende they be all one of byrthe, of lyfe, and of death, and of all other thyngꝭ of the body. And not one better than another to God warde, but onely by theyr good workes and dedes. And he that beleueth otherwyſe, beleueth folyouſlye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kynge aſked, whiche is the moſte delectable place in the worlde. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>THe moſte delectable place in the worlde, is there as the herte of
<pb facs="tcp:4834:15"/>man loueth, and hath wyll to be, for and a man were in the fayreſt place of the worlde, and had all that euer myghte be neceſſarye and nedefull to hym, and he loued another place bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that fayre place ſhulde lyke hym nought, agaynſt the loue that he had into another place, howe be it that it were ryght fowle. And yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were in the moſt vyleſt &amp; fowleſt place that is, and he loued well that place, yet he wold thynke that it were the moſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lectable place in the worlde, bycauſe that he loued it, and therfore we may ſay that the moſt delectable place it the world is there as the hert loueth and deſyreth, be it fayre or fowle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kyng aſked, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all this wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de was all water, was their in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any fyſſhe. Sydracke Anſwereth</head>
            <p>NAy forſoth, for when God mad other creatures he made all fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhes,
<pb facs="tcp:4834:16"/>for in the water there was no creature mouable, nor other creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res nor none other thinges but great Tenebres and derkenes, and in that water was the holy ghoſt, as a great lyght. And wyt yewel without doute that no Aungel nor Archaungell nor no creatur that euer was, nor is, nor ſhalbe, coulde not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that tyme for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde knowe all the puyſſaunce and the myght of God our creatoure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kynge aſked, whether is more the grauel of the erth, or the droppes of water of the ſee. Sydracke, An.</head>
            <p>THe Grauell of the erth is moch more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be the droppes of the water of the ſee. For one handefull of Grauell, mounteth a great quantyte of droppes of water. For the verye ſmall Sande and Grauell is moche ſmaller then the droppes of water.
<pb facs="tcp:4834:16"/>And the water may not be in no par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, but ſhe be vpon the erth and vpon the Grauell, and the Grauell ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the water and bereth it. And in many places in the world, Grauell is ryght great and ryght harde in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny partes of the worlde that a man ſhall fynde no drop of water, and in the depeſt of the ſee, it can not be ſo depe but that there is Grauel &amp; erth vnder the moſte depeſt. And therfore there is for one drop of water a .C. of Grauell. For all the water in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world reſteth vpon erth and vpon Grauell, and often tymes when a man taketh away the erth he fyndeth water, the hard Rocke, and that Rocke ſtandeth vpon Grauell. And for this reaſon, &amp; for the ſmalnes of the Grauell, and for the moſt parte where there is mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che Grauell, there is no drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Therfore the Grauell is moche more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the droppes of water in the
<pb facs="tcp:4834:17"/>ſee. But ye ſhall vnderſtande that we ſpeke not of the water, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuſtayneth and bereth all the erth in the worlde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kyng aſked myght a man no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre the droppes of the water of the ſee or the Grauell of the earth. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>AND the worlde were greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a .M. tymes, and a .M and were all ferme erth, and that it dured a .M. tymes a .M. yere goyng and were all enhabyted with folkes, the day and the nyght he .xxiiij. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and euerye houre is a .M. lxxx. poynctes, and in euery poyncte were borne a .M. M. tymes men, &amp; as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny women, and they were all full of heer, and for euery heer ſhulde haue a .M. M. tymes droppes. of water of the ſee. Yet the droppes of the ſee wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And yet the myſerycorde and the
<pb facs="tcp:4834:17"/>mercye of God is more then the one and the other, or all other thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world or were or ſhalbe vnto them that ſeke to haue it &amp; deſerue it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kyng aſked, whiche of the .vij. planettes gouerned the world before the tyme of Noes flodde. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>BEfore the tyme of Noes flodde there were .ij. Planettes that go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerned the world. And tho were Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnus &amp; Iupiter: and Mars began to gouerne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world before that flod .CC. xliiij. yere, for fro the begynnyng of Adam to the tyme of Noe it was ij. M. cc. xliiij. yere. And the .ij. M. yere gouerned Saturus and Iupiter, eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryche of them a .M. yere. And Mars began to gouerne the worlde before the flod of Noe .CC. xliiij. yere. And after Noes flod. Mars gouerned ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4834:18"/>his .M. yere were ended, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wyt, he gouerned after the fled .vii. C. lvi. yere. And nowe in out tyme Soll go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth the world, &amp; thus ſhall ende all the other Planettes, for eueryche of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall gouerne the world a .M. yere by the wyll and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of God. And when theſe .vij. M. yere be paſſed and and gone, from thenſe forth the world ſhall dure at the wyl, pleaſure &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, of almygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty God, for ferther I cannot ſay.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="question">
            <head>¶ The kyng aſked, of the goodnes &amp; harme that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of wyne. Sydracke, Anſwereth.</head>
            <p>NOble Kynge Alexandre, forget not to take tarte ſyropes in the mornyng faſtynge whan flumatyke humours abounde to moch. For it is profytable and waſteth them moche alſo I meruayle that any man may
<pb facs="tcp:4834:18"/>dye or be ſycke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eateth brede of clene and good wheete, holſome and good fleſſhe, and drynke good wyne of gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes temperatly. And yf he kepe hym fro to moch drynkyng, eatyng, &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle. Yf ſyckenes ouercome ſuche a man he muſt be healed as a dronken man. That is to wit he muſt be waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with warme water and than ſet ouer a rennyng water betwne .ij. gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne wylowes, and his ſtomacke anoyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an oyntment of ſandres, or ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dalles, &amp; haue a fumygacion of fran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenſence, and other ſwete ſpices, and it wyll do him moch good: and if any man wyll forſake holy the drynkyng of wyne ought not to leue in ſodeynly at ones but lytell &amp; ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, and to men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gle it euery day w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> water more &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, tyll at laſt there de nothing but cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re water: &amp; ſo he may kepe his helth and good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plection. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> gouerne thy body yf thou wylt lyue longe, and
<pb facs="tcp:4834:19"/>kepe my doctrynes, &amp; conſydre theſe thynges folowyng wherin nature co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forteth greatly. That is to wyt good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly paſtymes, ſyght of great richeſſes great reuerence, victory ouer enemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, fedynge on good meates, noyſe of mynſtralſy, ſyght of precious garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, often herynge of good tydynges ſpeche of wyſe men, to enquere of thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges paſt and to come, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion with fayre gentylwomen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>¶ FINIS. ¶</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge in the Duke of Suffolkes Rentes, beſyde chatynge Croſſe.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio, ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4834:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
